你们想没想过火箭入轨
Have you ever wondered, how do real-world rocket vehicles get to orbit
精度为什么那么高，能和将近8公里每秒
with such an accuracy, that they meet and dock with a space station
的空间站交会对接
traveling at almost eight kilometers per second?
一言以蔽之：这需要高深的算法
The short answer is: through some very ingenious algorithms
烧进火箭上的计算机里。而这样说你们又不高兴，那我今天
in their onboard computers. For the long answer:
就给你们传授一点人身经验：航天飞机导航算法
my name is Przemek, and this is Space Shuttle guidance
在坎巴拉太空计划里的实现。
done in Kerbal Space Program.
假设我们要给空间站送快递
So let's say we want to deliver some supplies to the International Space Station
而你之前也玩过KSP
Now, you've flown those missions before in Kerbal Space Program,
大家知道如果发射后进入的轨道比较好
and you know it's not so very hard to rendezvous,
交会就没那么难
once we're in a good orbit.
但如果你初始轨道和目标有倾角
But if your initial orbit is inclined to your target,
那就不好办了
things get pretty complicated.
所以这类发射中最重要、最难的部分
So the most difficult and important part of such launch
就是发射到停泊轨道
is the ascent to parking orbit.
所以我专门设计了一套上升段的自动驾驶
And I have created an ascent autopilot that does exactly that.
它用KOS编写
It was programmed in kOS
这MOD是坠吼的
(one of the best mods out there,
不知道的话，墙裂推荐！
so do look it up if you don't know it already)
它使用航天飞机算法来进行导航
and it uses the Space Shuttle's algorithm for orbital guidance.
我的代码实现非常的灵活
My implementation is flexible enough
适用于很多其他火箭
that we can run other vehicles too, so
而这个视频里我将使用Atlas V
to demonstrate, I'll use the Atlas V
来自MOD“Real Scale Boosters”
from Real Scale Boosters mod.
现在，使用我的代码，这类发射只要简单的
Now, using my autopilot, flying such missions is as easy as
选定目标
select target
输入“run PEGAS”
and run PEGAS.
最开始程序会计算发射窗口
And the first thing that happens is calculation of the launch window.
实际上只是粗略估计一下
In fact, it's just a rough estimate,
因为现实生活中这也很难精确计算
because in reality it's very difficult to calculate it precisely,
但我们只要粗略估计就行了
but we'll make do with that.
因为整个代码不需要发射窗口的算得有多精确
Fortunately the whole system is fairly insensitive to that
前后差一两分钟问题不大
and being off by a minute or two shouldn't be a big issue.
从这开始，火箭就完全交由PEGAS控制了
From this point, our vehicle is in complete control of PEGAS
姿态、分级都是它控制
which handles staging and attitude.
然后倒计时
So, we have the final countdown
RD-180点火
there should be the RD-180 ignition
AJ-60助推器点火，起飞！
and now the AJ-60s and liftoff!
发射分两个阶段
Now, there are usually two phases of ascent to orbit:
首先是在大气层内飞
and the first one, we're in now - atmospheric ascent.
这时候不用多精确
And the idea here is not so much about precision
飞得稳你就成功了
of what we're doing, as is about safety.
这时候主要目标是你的火箭完整的飞出大气层
We just want to get outside the atmosphere in one piece
别被风（动压）吹散架了
instead of breaking up due to high dynamic loads.
所以这里的逻辑
So the logic we're following
就是按照FAR的教程
is taken pretty much straight from ferram's Realism Overhaul tutorial,
起飞后给个俯仰角，然后
so basically pitch over by some known angle
保持零攻角一直飞
and hold attitude prograde at zero angle of attack.
当我们飞到大气足够稀的地方，动压小了
And once we've gained enough altitude that air density is no longer an issue,
就要切换到轨道学的、航天飞机导航算法了
then we will switch to orbital ascent using the Space Shuttle algorithm.
如果你们听过PEG
If you ever heard the word PEG
全称叫动力显式制导
or Powered Explicit Guidance, then this is exactly it,
就酱
this is one way of referring to it.
还有一点需要知道，绝大多数轨道导航算法
Now, the thing about most orbital guidance algorithms,
包括航天飞机，是不管大气层里的部分的
Shuttle's included, is that they do not take atmosphere into account at all.
我说绝大多数因为
Although take that with a grain of salt,
我真不知道最先进的算法是啥样的
as I don't know about the most modern algorithms.
因为空气动力学背后的数学
This is because maths behind aerodynamics
太特么难了，在天上飞的时候根本没法
are very complex and back then it couldn't be quickly
又快又好的算出来
and reliably solved mid-flight. So,
所以大气层内的阶段，最主要是
because in that phase the only thing that matters
是省油和精确（我觉得这里是口误，刚还说不用飞太准）
is precision and fuel efficiency,
我们现在等差不多了
we're better off waiting till we're above the air,
可以不管空气动力学了
so we can neglect its effects.
固推差不多该烧完了
And right about now the SRBs should be flaming out
我们等一会再扔
and we're going to jettison them a little later.
真实的Atlas V也是这样做的
This is actually what the real Atlas does,
火箭会带着烧完的固推再飞几秒
it carries them for a few seconds,
因为空气可能还没那么稀薄
as it might be unsafe to separate
扔太早不安全
if we're too low and the air is too dense, so
所以我们再飞一会
we carry them for a little bit.
现在自动导航激活
And now the automatic guidance will engage and
接管火箭姿态控制
take control of attitude.
但是谁硬点这算法叫“航天飞机导航算法”的？
But why the Space Shuttle and why the Shuttle's guidance algorithm
有什么特别的吗？
and what's so special about it?
Emmmm，说来话长
Well, to understand that
回到60年代
we need to go back in time to late 1960s
航天飞机还没造出来
when the Shuttle doesn't exist yet -
只是在图纸上和NASA产品经理嘴里存在的时候
not beyond drawing boards, proposals and requirements.
对于我们现在
And two of those requirements are of
最感兴趣的两点需求
particular interest to us right now.
一个是新飞船
The first one was the ability of the newly designed vehicle
能在轨建造空间站
to allow construction and servicing
of a low orbit space station,
也就是后来的
which will be later known as
国际空间站
the International Space Station.
另外是能把卫星从轨道上带回来
The other was the ability to retrieve satellites from orbit
而不止是送上去
and not just deliver them.
这两点需求有个共同点
Both those objectives have one thing in common:
需要轨道交会
they share a mission profile of an orbital rendezvous.
当然这不是什么新东西
This isn't to say that rendezvous was something new,
这点在之前的双子星座计划就演示过了
as the concept was demonstrated in the Gemini program before
阿波罗计划里也玩烂了
and used extensively in Apollo.
只是这从来没像这样
Just never before has this kind of
放进设计火箭的常规需求里
mission profile been a routine one.
因此，航天飞机需要一个全新的导航系统
So for this reason, among others,
the Shuttle needed an entirely new guidance algorithm.
于是70年代初
And indeed, in the early 70s
UPFG在德雷伯实验室设计出来了
the Unified Powered Flight Guidance was designed
by the Draper laboratory.
它叫"unified"（统一的）是因为这个系统
It was called "unified" because it was a single program
是为很多种飞行模式设计的
to handle many kinds of flight modes:
起飞、在轨机动终止一直到离轨点火
ascent, abort through orbital maneuvers, up to deorbit burn.
当然这里我只实现了
Out of those I only implement the
标准的起飞模式
standard ascent mode in my autopilot,
过会我会详细解释
and I will describe it in a bit more detail in a moment,
因为我们马上要改变发动机工作模式了
because now we're approaching a burn mode change.
之前发动机是全推力状态
Previously the engine was set at full throttle,
但如果继续这样
but if we continued on like that,
载荷会承受8G的力量
we'd soon reach acceleration in excess of 8 Gs -
这对载荷很不好
which isn't good for the payload at all.
所以我们慢慢收油门
So we're going to throttle down gradually
把G值限制在4.5
to limit acceleration at about 4.5 Gs.
航天飞机会限制在3G
The Shuttle itself had a 3 G limit in place
来保护乘组
to protect the crew.
接下来是另一组事件
And another set of pre-timed events occurs now:
抛整流罩
we first jettison the payload fairing
然后抛半人马上面级的FLR
and now the Centaur Fairing Load Reactor.
然后引擎关机
And now we have engine cutoff
然后分离
and a separation sequence,
这也是由PEGAS控制的，完全可以自定义
which is controlled by PEGAS, and fully customizable.
然后是CCB分离
First the Common Core Booster separates,
然后半人马上面级沉底发动机启动
then ullage motors activate on the Centaur,
然后点火
and there's the ignition,
接着UPFG再次接手火箭姿态控制
and UPFG soon after takes control of the attitude again.
咱们看看我们做的如何，轨道看上去不错
So let's see how we're doing. The orbit looks pretty good
程序告诉我们还有四百秒
and the algorithm reports time to go of about 400 seconds
应该足够我
which will be just about enough time to
解释下UPFG的法则了
explain the basic principle behind UPFG.
但在问“怎么控制”之前
But before we focus on "how" let's answer
我们先说它到底在“控制啥”——火箭飞控的中心思想
"what" it really does - the very idea of rocket guidance.
总的来说，我们要把一个已知的火箭
As a general principle, we want to steer a known vehicle
火箭的当前状态已知
which has a known current state
送进一个目标状态
into some target state
这在发射阶段来说就是某种轨道
which in the ascent mode happens to be some kind of orbit.
现在轨道多数是用一组轨道根数来描述的
Now, this orbit is most likely described with a set of orbital elements
比如半长轴、偏心率
such as semi-major axis and eccentricity
或者你喜欢听的近地点远地点
or apoapse and periapse if you prefer,
还有倾角、升交点赤经
and inclination and longitude of ascending node.
然而这就很难受
It's very uncomfortable however -
你要是想只改远地点
if you've ever tried changing just your apoapse
玩过KSP的都知道你必须在近地点才行
you know it's impossible unless you're currently at periapse.
改倾角和升交点赤经也同理
Similar thing with inclination and LAN -
想只改一个而不影响其他的条件太苛刻了
it's hard to change one without the other,
这对导航来说很不好
which isn't good for guidance at all.
而理想情况下，我们想在某个直观的数学坐标系下
Ideally, we'd like to work with some mathematically sane coordinate system, like
比如笛卡尔XYZ坐标系
Cartesian XYZ system.
在这坐标系里描述点P的位置非常直观
In XYZ it's fairly easy to describe our current state,
但对于描述目标轨道就不一定了
but it's not the same with a target orbit.
毕竟轨道不是一个点，而是一整个椭圆
After all, orbit is not a single point but a whole ellipse of them,
所以用笛卡尔坐标系也不太现实
so such description is not really possible.
但如果给定XYZ位置和速度
However if we were given some XYZ position and velocity,
我们可以很容易的确定我们轨道好不好
we could easily verify whether it is a good orbit or not -
——只要检查速度倾角、姿态这些就行
simply by checking altitude velocity angle and the like.
结果就是，这就足够我们做精确的导航了
And it turns out, this is enough to do very precise guidance.
而这里的关键在于
One remaining thing is the vehicle -
我们得知道我们当前状态如何
after all, we need to know exactly what are we steering.
简言之，我们有很多参数是已知的
In general, there will be plenty of parameters we could write down about it,
但从火箭的角度来讲
but from the point of view of rocket motion,
最后只有四个有用的
it all boils down to just four:
火箭干重
dry mass of the vehicle,
剩余燃料重量
mass of the propellant it has in the tanks
还有两个火箭的参数
and parameters of its engines:
推力和比冲
combined thrust and specific impulse.
说白了就是：多重、推力多大、油耗如何
So basically, how much does it weigh,
how hard can it push itself and how efficiently can it do that.
而对于多级火箭
And if we have a multi-stage vehicle,
每一级都有这些参数
there will be those four numbers per each stage -
这就又很难受
which in turn isn't so very comfortable to
很难把它们放进统一的数学公式里
plug into any mathematical equation.
所以设计导航的dalao们
So the clever guys from guidance
发明了“推力积分”
came up with something called thrust integrals.
我不会在这细讲这些
I will not give a detailed explanation of them here,
怕你们睡着
as this would be unnecessarily boring,
只是说明这个方法给我们带来多大便利
just outline the greatest advantage they give us.
推力积分让我们能合并
The thrust integrals allow us to coalesce
火箭的各级参数
the vehicle description into one set of numbers,
无论火箭是怎么分级的
irregardless of the number of stages.
所以多亏这个
So, thanks to that,
多级火箭的导航
the capability to guide multistage vehicles
其实就是在做算法
is kind of built into the algorithm itself.
即使航天飞机没有完全使用这些
Even though the Shuttle did not really make full use of that,
因为航天飞机主要部分其实还是单级的
for the major part it was a single stage vehicle,
它上面的OMS发动机只用来圆轨
the OMS thrusters were used only to circularize.
我只是解释一下
And it just so happens that I've explained the
UPFG第一个重要部分
first important part of UPFG:
推力积分的计算而已
calculation of the thrust integrals.
那么我们先总结一下
So let's recap what have we found out so far.
我们知道火箭状态如何
We know what vehicle we're steering,
知道我们在哪
we know where we are
但不知道我们接下来要向哪里导航
we don't know where we want to be.
但这有办法知道
But we have a way of figuring out
我们的路径（如果有的话）是好的
whether our destination - if we had one - is a good one.
严格来说我们不知道我们接下来会到哪
The fact that we essentially don't know where we're going
这好像有点麻烦
might seem like a bit of a problem, but
但假设我们猜测到了未来的准确位置
let's assume for now that we somehow guessed the exact destination.
我们有XYZ位置和速度矢量
We have some XYZ position and velocity vector.
以此计算还差多远
From that we could calculate the distance we need to cover
还差多少速度
and the velocity we need to gain.
这就是“还要多少速度”
This is exactly this velocity-to-go,
即视频中左边窗口内的“v-go”
the v-go marker that you see in PEGAS interface.
可以看成是
It can be thought of as
你还需要多少DV
maneuver delta-v which you're used to.
这样我们就能计算
Knowing our vehicle, we can also calculate
获得这些速度还要多久
how long will it take to gain that velocity,
也就是窗口里的“t-go”
and this is the time to go - the t-go - marker.
于是有了航天飞机多年使用的技术
Now, there is a technique, known for years prior to the Shuttle,
它能直接从当前状态与目标状态
that allows directly calculating pitch and yaw angles,
计算俯仰与偏航角
given the current and target states.
称为“线性正切制导律”
This is called Linear Tangent Guidance,
这也是我们最开始使用推力积分的原因
and it's the main reason we needed those thrust integrals to begin with.
抓住一点
It only has one catch:
既然普通的方法计算重力和推力
since general solution for gravity and thrust
在数学上很难
is mathematically difficult,
就像空气动力学一样
just like aerodynamics,
那么LTG算法就假设地球是平的
the LTG assumes the Earth is flat,
而重力矢量恒不变
and the gravity vector never changes.
这显然不对
Which is obviously wrong,
所以我们结果也是错的
so our result will be wrong because in reality,
现实中地球是圆的，重力方向也会变
the spherical Earth's gravity will pull us down differently.
所以设计UPFG的人
So the guys who designed UPFG
想到一个绝妙的办法来修正
came up with a neat way to correct that.
他们设计一个函数来预测火箭未来
They designed a function to predict the future state of a vehicle
只受重力条件下的状态
in free motion under just gravity,
叫做圆锥状态推断
called Conic State Extrapolation, and then
然后想办法把推力加进去
figured out a way to incorporate thrust into it.
这样就有了一个还不错的未来状态推断
This way, they ended up with a decent future state predictor,
以此，我们可以
using which we can:
先用线性正切制导律粗略计算
first calculate a rough guidance using Linear Tangent,
然后使用圆锥状态推断
then use Conic State Extrapolation
来知道未来重力矢量是什么样的
to find out what the gravity vector really would be like,
用这个结果再重新计算
and save that knowledge for the next run.
再次调用LTG
Plug it back into the LTG,
逐渐校准提高计算结果的准确度
gradually increasing the accuracy of its results.
实际上最开始的误差
But in fact, the initial inaccuracy
可能不只是对重力方向处理上的误差
might not be only due to bad gravity handling.
我们可能压根目标状态都猜错
We simply might have guessed our target wrong -
而这也能校准
would be good to correct for that too.
所以UPFG并不是
And the way UPFG approaches that
慢慢修改我们最初的猜测
is not by slowly correcting our initial guess.
而是直接找一个与猜测最接近的
Instead it finds an entirely new target position,
全新的目标状态
that is nearest to the predicted one,
然后把之前的猜测直接删掉
and discards our guess at all in the process.
再利用新的目标，循环整个算法
And with this new target, the whole algorithm runs again.
最后总结一下，我们最开始猜测我们未来的状态
So, to sum up: we start by guessing some destination,
以此计算俯仰偏航
we calculate pitch and yaw angles
使用线性正切制导律
to get there using Linear Tangent,
再用圆锥状态推断修正重力
we use Conic State to correct for the gravity,
从而找一个新的未来状态
and we verify our guess in the target by picking a new one.
然后使用这个新值，算法循环进行
And then we run the algorithm again
with that new value.
如果我们重复这个过程几次
And if we repeat this process several times,
误差就会越来越小
the error will get smaller and smaller as we go,
最终小到可以说是真实结果了
and at some point it will become so little,
that we might safely say that a true solution has been found -
因为已经没有误差了
one that has no errors anymore.
这时我们称
And when that happens,
算法收敛了
we say that the algorithm has converged.
从此我们就能遵循它的导航了
From then on we can follow its guidance.
所以就酱
So there you have it,
我想我差不多形容出来
I hope I have at least outlined the
航天飞机导航算法的大致轮廓了
Space Shuttle guidance algorithm.
当然我没讲非常细
Of course, I didn't go into much detail
因为这里面很复杂
as this would be very complex and
十分钟肯定不够
definitely not just for a 10 minute video.
但你想要了解更多的话
But if you want to know more,
欢迎查看评论区和视频说明
do check the description for this one.
我会把原YouTuber给的参考资料全放进去
I've written a much more thorough explanation
以及他在Gayhub上的KOS代码
of the algorithm on my github pages.
所以如果你感兴趣
So if you're interested in the all intricacies
and bells and whistles of UPFG,
记得看哦！
then please do check it out.
现在我们快要
And right about now we're getting to the
到主引擎关机了
the main engine cutoff,
应该还剩几秒
which should be in a few seconds.
OK
And there we have it.
PEGAS说任务成功了
PEGAS says mission successful
所以我们看看轨道参数
so let's take a look at the parameters:
倾角和升交点赤经看上去很完美
inclination and longitude of ascending node look perfect,
角度相差0度
angle between orbits: 0 degrees.
远地点近地点可能差一点
Apoapse and periapse might look a little bit off,
但我个人觉得
but I think, not sure, but I think they are within
已经在Atlas V火箭的精度内了
actual accuracy limits of the
Atlas V vehicle.
然后我们看看接下来会和点火有多难
But let's see how difficult would it be
to plan a transfer maneuver from this parking orbit,
然后我们看看接下来会和点火有多难
if we wanted to rendezvous with the Space Station.
我加速提高远地点
So if we just raise our apoapse
直到轨道相切
till we get a little intersect...
像这样
just like that...
然后调整下时间
and now if we do that a little later,
几圈之后再机动
a few orbits later, then we should probably be
会和点就会接近
getting close.
看看
Let's check that out.
应该会有个很不错的交会条件
We should get a pretty reasonable intersect.
有了
Oh, there we have it -
200米
200 meters.
最近处相距200米
200 meters intersect
我自己手动调的霍曼转移
by a maneuver I planned within what,
只用了差不多十秒吧？
10 seconds?
我觉得OK
Well, that's it,
感谢观看
I hope you've enjoyed watching it,
剩下的还是看评论区吧
if you want to test PEGAS yourself,
the links are in the description so you can download it right away.
剩下的还是看评论区吧
Tutorials are included so you can try it yourself
with hopefully little pain.
剩下的还是看评论区吧
Once again, thanks for watching
my name is Przemek and that was
剩下的还是看评论区吧
Space Shuttle guidance algorithm
done in Kerbal Space Program.
剩下的还是看评论区吧
Fly accurately!